Arrival isn't just an impressive piece
of storytelling involving time and
space. It's a film that forces your
brain to renegotiate how time and space
work.
And that
is quite something.
Because cinema is always screwing with
[music] your sense of time and space.
Through its native language, the way it
cuts, moves, and rearranges what we see,
it takes your perception for a ride
every time you [music] engage with it.
It just hides its manipulation and
preserves your sense of orientation by
playing into this thing called
continuity.
And I don't mean production level
continuity or the avoidance of [music]
continuity errors as it's more commonly
known. No.
I mean perceptual continuity. The unique
ability of our brains to connect
discontinuous [music]
images in a way that makes changes in
our visual or even temporal [music]
perspectives feel seamless.
My previous video was actually [music]
focused entirely on this subject. If you
haven't seen it yet, maybe head there
after this video for a more
comprehensive run-through.
In the meantime, for a simple but great
example of what I'm talking about here,
have a quick look at this clip from
season 3 of Fargo.
I mean, you're practically all grown up.
I just
Phone's for you, Chief. Nope, Deputy.
Here, blocking and cutting on action,
specifically the action of this guy
entering the frame behind Gloria, are
used to make the transition [music] from
this medium shot to this wider shot far
more continuous. Even though, by way of
the cut and changing perspective, it's
anything but. As this example
illustrates, most of the time these
manipulations are almost invisible. Yes,
our reality [music] is being rearranged,
but it's done using a language that
keeps us firmly orientated in both time
and space. So, what makes Arrival so
different, even now 10 years since its
release? Well, instead of pandering to
our comfort with continuity by imitating
our brains' predictive processing
mechanisms, Denis Villeneuve
turns them against us. In doing so,
Arrival [music]
takes this concept of perceptual
continuity and breaks it.
Villeneuve does [music] this by using
temporal misdirection to exploit a
fundamental cognitive bias in film
watching. We generally assume anything
intercut with the present [music] is
context, and most often that context is
the past.
Arrival feeds us images that we
naturally interpret as Louise's past
memories, [music]
at least on our first viewing, only to
reveal at the end, during the film's
apex, that these were in fact Louise's
memories of the future. I don't
understand.
Who is this child?
Which recontextualizes the entire
narrative in a way that forces us to
structurally reinterpret everything
[music] we've just seen. And while it's
true that we've been manipulated into
wrongly using these images to inform our
understanding of Louise's character, as
well as the order of events throughout
the entire story, Villeneuve's deception
exposes the film as something [music]
more than just a cool example of how
editing shapes meaning.
It transforms Arrival into a film that
doesn't [music] just play with time. It
plays with the very processes we use to
make sense of it. It's Villeneuve
turning the conventional grammar of
cinema into the subject [music] of
cinema and wielding it against us. And
that's what makes this type of cinema so
powerful. It's cinema that doesn't just
entertain, it also deliberately and
structurally violates our patterns of
everyday perception.
>> [music]
>> We enter experiences like Arrival with
our typical understanding of cinema's
language and, more importantly, of our
reality. If we're shown memories,
they'll be of the past. Time is linear,
and our experience of it is
one-directional, only to have these
expectations turned on their head when
the truth finally lands. What happens
next is a large-scale prediction error,
and suddenly our brains are forced to
reconstruct an entirely new model of
reality. They're experiences that
stretch, strain, and reassemble our
perceptual habits and expectations in
ways that don't just reshape their
narratives, they disrupt the basic
[music] assumptions we rely on to
understand how time and space work at
all. This sort of reconstruction is
different. It's effortful, and effortful
experiences tend to feel far more
meaningful, particularly when, in cases
like Arrival, we're dealing with a
reconstruction that extends beyond the
story and starts [music] to challenge
the basic rules of our reality.
By attacking our experience of memory,
time, and our spatio-temporal
orientation, Arrival shifts something
fundamental and momentarily destabilizes
the sense of coherence we typically
operate with. Not permanently, not
traumatically, but safely.
>> [music]
>> And this controlled destabilization of
reality is key. As humans, we don't just
tolerate [music] this destabilization,
we often seek it out. We're drawn to
experiences that challenge our sense of
normality. It's what attracts us to
roller coasters, to existential [music]
philosophy, to magic tricks. But most
importantly, it's what draws us to
cinematic experiences like Arrival that
force us to question our understanding
of the world as we know it.
Of course, not every film that plays
with time and space produces this
[music] effect. The difference is scale
and intent. Whether those manipulations
are used instrumentally, simply to
entertain and serve a story, [music]
or whether they're pushed far enough to
challenge the way we perceive and
process reality. Films, shows, and
sequences that harness time and [music]
space like this are doing something that
even the ordinary tricks of cinema can't
do. Where conventional cinema does
inherently rearrange our reality, its
language is gentle. It guides our
perception and keeps us orientated.
We're never psychologically [music] or
philosophically unmoored by its
illusions. This is true even in stories
that radically depart from our world.
We're able to sit through things like
The Lord of the Rings, Harry Potter, or
Dune without feeling genuinely
disorientated because, although they're
changing a lot, they're not changing
enough to make our brains hiccup.
[music] No matter how fantastical things
get, the core pillars of reality, time,
space, memory, identity,
>> [music]
>> remain stable
most of the time. And that makes even
the most outlandish worlds feel
coherent. Our internal model of a
steady, continuous reality simply isn't
being challenged strongly enough to
create a problem for our brains'
predictive way of experiencing the
world. So, even in the face of Balrogs,
all-powerful rings, and undead armies,
everything updates smoothly, and our
brains [music] keep us orientated. In
Arrival, though, the challenge is strong
enough.
>> [music]
>> It raises the stakes by elevating its
handling of time and space from the
purely instrumental to something
genuinely existential. It shatters the
cognitive scaffolding we rely on to feel
secure in reality, temporarily
overwriting our internal model of time,
of space, of memory, and allowing us to
inhabit a version of reality that is
fundamentally alien to our embodied
human experience, a reality not bound by
time.
It's a cinematic experience that demands
active reconstruction rather than one
that lets our perceptions run on
autopilot. And when that reconstruction
settles, the world feels slightly
different, not because reality has
literally changed, but because our
understanding of it has. Just like
Louise is gifted a language that
violates her own sense of perceptual
continuity and allows her to experience
time in a truly non-linear sense, the
film [music] gives us the same gift.
It's by no means the only film to push
us this far, but few make something this
grand, this cosmically vast, feel this
intimate. That's why Arrival isn't just
an impressive piece of storytelling
involving time and space. It's a film
that forces your brain to renegotiate
[music]
how time and space work.
And that
is quite something.
>> [music]